These dishes
这些菜
were made by your dad.
都是你爸亲手做的
Eat some.
来
Mom,
妈
My condition is different from Mengxin.
我不是梦心
I had a natural labor. No need to feed me.
我是顺产 不用喂
I'll eat it by myself.
我自己来吧
But your hand...
那你这手
Take care. It hurts.
你小心点疼
I'm fine.
没事
Little Grape.
小葡萄
I had a natural labor.
我呢 是顺产
The doctor said I could walk tomorrow
大夫说了 明天能下地
and I'll be out one day later.
后天就能出院了
Don't walk.
下什么地呀
Look.
你这
You're in postnatal confinement.
坐月子 我跟你说
You've to have a good rest.
你可得好好休养
Or you'll develop chronic illnesses later.
你要不然以后落下病根
The doctor said
大夫说了
I could walk.
可以下地走一走
It's helpful
这样对身体恢复
in body recovery.
也有好处
The doctor said it.
大夫说了
Well.
那那那
Then you can take a little walk.
那就适当走走呗
You need to rest and recuperate properly.
你得好好养着
Women suffer a lot to deliver a baby.
这女人生孩子太辛苦了
I know this quite well.
我可是知道
I'm so happy to see the baby.
看着这孩子是真高兴
Meng'an,
梦安
it's worth the time and effort, isn't it?
辛苦也值了吧
Little Grape.
小葡萄
Jing.
他大姑
Having a second child at this age
我们安安这么大岁数
is not easy for An.
生二胎不容易
Yes.
是
She suffers a lot.
辛苦
It's okay.
还行
Giving birth to a baby at my age
我觉得这个年纪
may postpone
生个二胎
my menopause for a few years.
更年期都会晚好几年的
Stubborn.
嘴硬
Just eat it.
你赶紧 赶紧吃
Quickly. It's getting cold.
赶紧吃 凉了
Meng'an.
梦安
My husband
老欧阳
sent me
给这个
Little Grape's
小葡萄起的名字
names on my phone.
发过来了
Wanna check them?
你要不要看看
No, no.
不不不
She can't be staring at the phone screen.
现在不能看手机
No.
不能看手机
It's alright.
没事
Nope!
怎么没事啊
Too much phone time during
那坐月子看手机看多了
postnatal confinement will hurt your eyes.
眼睛要瞎的
Fine.
行行行
No more watching it.
不看了 不看了
I'll read it to you.
这样 我给你念啊
Listen up.
你听着
Li Haoyu.
李浩宇
Li Jialin.
李嘉林
Li Ruixian.
李瑞贤
Li Ruixian is a very nice name, isn't it?
这李瑞贤是不是挺好的
It's meaningful.
这名字显得挺有内涵的
Well,
那个
Jing,
他大姑
giving baby's name
这孩子名字现在不着急
can wait.
咱们以后再说
I suggest
这样
we go back first.
咱们先回去吧
Look,
这个
Meng'an didn't sleep well last night.
安安昨晚一晚没睡好
She looks tired.
你看看她今天
Just eat some and go to sleep.
吃点东西就赶紧睡啊
We've disturbed her rest.
我们在这儿耗她精神
Let's go back. Go.
走走走 咱们先回去
It's okay.
那没事
You can leave first.
你要回你先回
It's a mess here.
你看这儿很乱
I've to tidy up
一会儿吃完了
after she eats it.
我还得收拾呢
Besides, she needs me to attend her.
再说这儿没人不行
No need. Xin is coming right away.
不 心心马上就来
Well, don't worry about me.
你看你 你不用操心我
Jing,
他大姑
you didn't get much rest last night.
你昨晚上就没休息好
And you haven't eaten either.
你看你也没吃什么
Why don't you come to my place
这样 你到我那儿去
and let me cook you some food?
我给你弄点好吃的
You can have a good rest there.
完了好好休息休息
I've learned traditional Chinese medicine.
我这是学中医出身
I'm good at health maintenance.
擅长养生
Taking a day or two to look after her
你说这熬一两天
is not a big deal.
这算什么呀
Though you studied TCM
你 你学中医是不是
and you can keep healthy,
你养生
you have to eat
那你也得吃饭
and sleep.
你也得睡觉不是
Or it's harmful to your body.
你身体可不能垮
You know?
我跟你说
Go, go.
走走走
Go back!
回去 回去啊
Are you okay to stay here by yourself?
你自己在这儿行吗
I'm okay.
行
Jing,
大姐
you go to my mom's home
你到我妈那儿去
to have a meal
就吃饭
and take some sleep.
就睡觉
No need to do anything else, okay?
什么都不用管啊
Okay.
好
Wait.
等一下
Little Grape,
小葡萄
I'm leaving.
大姑先走了啊
I'll come back to see you soon.
回头来看你啊
Let's go.
行了 行了
I don't bear to leave him.
可舍不得了
Yeah.
是是是
I just wanna see him.
我就 我就想看他
Take you time to eat it.
你慢点吃啊
Uncle, press here.
叔 你按一下
Yeah. Otherwise, it will all stick up.
对 要不都翘起来了
Decorate red eggs with stickers?
贴喜蛋呢
Jing!
姐
Look,
你看咱们家
everyone is busy event this happy event.
这俩好合一好啊
Mr. Xu,
老爷子
did you check the name?
名字看了吗
The name
就是让老欧阳
my husband gave.
起的那几个名字
It's in the house.
在屋里 走
Come!
来来来
Jing,
他大姑
can we talk
那个给孩子起名的事
about naming the baby?
我还想跟你商量商量
Ms. Wu,
大姨
If you think
如果你要是觉得
the name given by my husband
我们家老欧阳
isn't good,
起得不行
it doesn't matter.
没关系
You can find an expert
你再找高人
to think out new ones.
咱再起一轮
I'm sure we can get
一定能起一个
a name we're happy with.
满意的名字
I didn't mean that.
我不是这意思
Look,
我是说呀
I've also got names for the baby.
我也找人起了些名
Do you like to take a look?
要不你看看
Okay.
好啊
Let me see.
那我看看
You all give a lot of care.
真是 都费心了啊
Xu Zirui,
许子瑞
Xu Ziqi.
许子齐
Ms. Wu,
大姨
what do you mean?
你什么意思
Let me explain.
是这样
My husband and I have discussed it
那个 梦安这个老二啊
with Meng'an and Li Lin,
出生前我跟梦安 李临
before the baby
还有老许
was born.
我们都商量过
Hua is your eldest son.
华华是你们家长子吧
His surname is Li.
他姓李
He took his maternal grandpa's last name.
随了老爷子的姓
His grandpa's wish
这不了却了
was fulfilled, right?
老爷子的一个心愿吗
So, I just thought
这梦安这老二
about letting
我就想着
the baby
能不能
take the surname
跟我们老许家的姓
of the Xu family.
姓许
Does Li Lin agree?
李临同意吗
They all agreed.
李临他们都同意了
I don't agree!
我不同意
Little Grape is a boy.
小葡萄是个男孩
The Li family's only grandson.
我们老李家唯一的根
His last name must be Li!
他必须姓李
Jing, take it easy.
他大姑 你别着急
It's not about the gender.
这跟男孩女孩没关系
You know,
那个
when we discussed it,
我们商量的时候
we didn't know Meng'an's baby
也不知道梦安肚子里
was a boy or a girl.
是男孩女孩啊
I just wanna
我就想
fulfill the wish of my husband.
替老许了个心愿
Can you understand it?
理解吧
I can't!
不理解
Jing,
姐
Jing, are you not having a meal here?
姐 你不吃饭了
I'm pissed off!
气吃饱了
What's wrong?
出啥事了 姨
Here you are. Let's stick together.
来 贴喜蛋
Take it.
来
It breaks.
碎了
Great!
碎了好
It breaks bad luck.
岁岁平安
It's all about naming.
都是名字惹的祸
You're even laughing?
还笑
Wake up!
你还睡
Jing,
姐
let me sleep a little longer.
再让我睡一会儿
I had a poor sleep last night.
我昨天晚上就没睡好
I've to go to the hospital
我一会儿还得上医院
to take care of Meng'an later.
陪梦安呢
Something big has happened.
出大事了
What's wrong?
什么大事
Is it about Little Grape?
小葡萄
Little Grape's last name has been changed.
小葡萄改姓了
What?
什么
Yes, Little Grape takes the surname Xu.
对 小葡萄姓许了
This is serious!
这么大的事
You didn't tell me!
你跟谁商量了
Lin.
临临
Have some orange juice.
来 喝 喝杯橙汁
Okay.
行
This isn't orange juice
这不是橙汁
judging from its color.
这颜色
It doesn't matter.
没事 没事
I'll drink it.
都行 都行
I forgot it.
忘了 忘了
You don't like sweet drinks.
你不爱喝甜的
I'm into it.
这个 我爱喝 爱喝
Lin,
临临
since Little Grape was born,
那小葡萄出生之后
have you thought about his name?
他的大名你想过没啊
No, we haven't.
我们还没想到这块儿呢
Not yet?
没想呢
Right.
对
Listen,
我跟你说
I came up with a few ones.
我倒是想了几个
Really?
是吗
Great, Mom.
行啊 妈
Tell me about them.
那那 说说看
The name of your sister's son
你那个大姐的儿子
is Hua.
是叫华华
Right?
对吧
His last name is Li?
他姓李吧
Yes, right.
对 姓李
Let me explain.
这么回事
When my sister and my brother-in-law
我大姐和大姐夫
got married,
结婚那会儿
my dad made my brother-in-law
我爸不是把所有的一切
take charge of everything.
都交给姐夫管了吗
So, after they had
有了孩子之后呢
a son and a daughter,
一儿一女
the boy took the last name Li,
男孩呢 就随我们李姓
while the girl's last name is Ouyang.
女孩呢 就随欧阳姓了
Great! What a harmonious relationship!
多好呀 两好并一好
Yeah, exactly.
对 两好并一好
Right?
是吧
We worked together.
两好并一好
So,
那那个
after your second baby is born,
老二生出来之后
the baby's last name will be Xu?
就姓许吧
okay.
行
Okay?
行啊
Will the last name be Xu?
姓许
Yes.
对呀
Let's get closer as a family!
两好并一好
How nice it is!
多好呀
Isn't it?
是吧
I knew it.
我就知道
Lin, you're educated
临临 你有文化
and reasonable.
讲道理
I knew you'd agree.
我就知道你肯定能答应
I've talked over with your father-in-law.
我都跟你爸商量好了
I'll get you some soda water.
我给你换杯苏打水
No, no. I...
不不不 我
Have we reached an agreement?
商量好了
Were you told
是
by Meng'an's mother?
梦安她妈妈跟你说的吧
You're a fool!
你说你傻不傻呀
If Little Grape is a girl,
小葡萄是个女孩
it's okay.
咱也就算了
But he's a son.
可他是个儿子
Our mom passed away early.
咱妈走得早
Our dad cared much
咱爸对这个姓氏的事
about the continuation of the last name.
特别在意
If you change Little Grape's last name,
你要是把姓给改了
the Li family line won't be existed.
咱老李家可就没了
I understand.
懂
But what you said
但是你这说的
isn't right.
也 也不准确啊
How could it be gone?
怎么就没了呢
Doesn't Hua
这华华
take
不就是
the last name Li?
跟着我们李家姓吗
It's not same.
这能一样吗
When Yungjie was born,
你当时生完云阶的时候
you didn't plan to have a second child.
你也没说要二胎了
Hua's last name was changed to Li
我是没办法
as I had no option.
我才把华华改姓李的
It's all
我这不都是为了
for the Li family line.
咱们老李家吗
Yes.
是 是 是
When Meng'an was pregnant with 2nd child
这 我们怀二胎的时候
we didn't know
也不知道
it'd be a boy or a girl.
他是男孩还是女孩啊
No more talking about it. It's irrelevant.
不说这些的 越说越远
I know your intention.
明白你的意思
Fine.
行
You can change it if you want.
你要想改也行
But you've to change Yunjie's last name.
你让云阶姓许
Nonsense!
又瞎说了
How can Yunjie's last name be Xu?
云阶怎么能姓许呢
She is fifteen years old.
云阶已经十五岁了
It can't be changed
不能改
and it's hard to do it.
也不好改
Little Grape's surname can't be changed.
小葡萄也不能改
Jing,
姐
relax.
你不要心急
I'll discuss it
这个事
with Meng'an
我跟她妈妈一起来商量
and then talk with her other families.
跟他们家说
Don't get yourself involved in.
你就不要掺和了
When you step in,
你一操心这个事吧
a small thing
一小事
could develop
就
into a serious problem.
就变成大事了
How can this be a trivial matter?
这怎么能是小事呢
You're the eldest son.
你是长子
Little Grape is the eldest grandson.
小葡萄是长孙
This is
这对我们李家来讲
a big deal to the Li family.
这就是大事
Okay.
行
Don't worry.
放心吧
I'll definitely
我一定会给你一个
find the best solution to it.
满意的答复
Aright.
行
I'll be waiting for it.
我等着
If you can't give me a satisfied answer,
要是结果不满意
I won't leave here.
我就不走了
The soup Jing made
姐这汤做得
is so tasty.
真是太好喝了
I've to talk to you.
我跟你说个事
Jing
就 我姐
went to your mom's home.
不是上咱妈那儿去了吗
When she got back,
回来以后就
she was upset.
不太高兴
Why?
为什么呀
For...
就是
For the naming?
因为起名的事
You've known it?
你知道了
When Mom urged Jing to return with her,
我妈拽大姐走的时候
I've found her intention.
不要太明显
My mom
你说这老太太
was splitting hairs.
是不是钻了牛角尖了
I thought Jing
我还以为大姐
was not gonna cook for me anymore.
不会再给我做饭了呢
Not possible.
那不能
Jing said
大姐还说了
you needed to have more soup
你得多喝汤
for detox.
有利排毒
Jing is so nice.
大姐真好
What do you think
那你的想法呢
about the naming?
这事
What about your thought?
你什么想法啊
I...
我
I'm not that fussed.
我 我无所谓
He's my son,
姓什么
no matter what his last name is.
他 他都是我儿子
Right?
是吧
Can you just tell me the truth?
能不能说句实话
Biologically speaking,
就是从生理基因上来讲
I'm okay with it.
我很舒服
Though his last name could be Li,
那
he's still my son.
姓什么他都是我儿子
Right?
对吧
However,
但是
traditionally speaking,
如果从传统理念上来讲
I'm not
你说我心里舒服
okay with it.
那是假话
So, it depends on what I value most.
就是看这比重是多少了
My mom
你说说我妈
got an idea
随随便便一个想法
and put us in a pickle.
就把我们搞得这么为难
Won't she
她都不知道
feel sorry for the baby?
心疼一下孩子吗
She had that idea
咱妈有这个想法
with a reason.
也不是随随便便的
You may not understand.
你可能不理解
Let me help you figure out
我跟你分析一下
the Xu family's situation.
你们老许家的情况啊
I don't need you view
我们家情况
my family situation.
还用你分析呀
She just felt sorry that
不就是她觉得
she didn't give birth a son
没给我爸生个儿子
for my dad.
对不起老头吗
But why didn't she find a way out earlier?
那你早干吗去了呀
Why does she have to bother us about it?
折磨我们干什么呀
It's no use talking about it now.
你现在说这些没用
Now that she asked for it,
她既然这么说了
we should
那这个事
fix the problem.
就要有个结果
And
再说了
your dad talked with me about it as well.
你爸也跟我讲过
My dad?
我爸
When was it?
什么时候啊
What did he say?
他怎么说的
He said, "Li Lin,
李临
if your mother-in-law asks about this,
你妈要是问起来
tell her
你就说
I've already talked with you about it.
我跟你已经说过了
It's your turn."
该你了
My dad!
这老爷子
He went too far!
也是够了
He only cares my mom's feeling.
他不就是心疼他媳妇吗
Though he cares my mom,
你心疼媳妇
it's his
关起门来爱怎么心疼
business.
怎么心疼
Why did he torture you by saying that?
折磨你干吗呀
Don't you care about me?
你不心疼媳妇啊
Yes, I do.
我心疼啊
That's enough of that.
不说了
We'll talk about this matter later.
这个事 回头再说啊
The problem can't be avoided.
这是回头再说的事吗
Li Lin, you know what?
我跟你讲 李临
It lies on
这事说大不大
how we treat this naming matter.
说小也不小
Seriously speaking,
往大了说
it bears on the family lines.
是两个家族的事
On a smaller scale,
往小了说
it is matter of our family.
就是咱一家三口的事
Since it's our family issue,
那既然是一家三口的事
we'll talk about it together
就等云阶来
when Yunjie comes.
等她来了咱一块儿商量
Good idea.
好主意
I take your point.
我同意
It has to be fixed
这个事
in a democratic way.
我们要民主
No!
我不改
Why do I have to change it?
我凭什么改呀
As Little Grape is a boy,
就因为小葡萄是男的
you ask me to change my last name?
就让我改姓 是吗
No, no.
不是 不是 不是
Listen.
是这样子
If your last name is Xu,
其实你姓许
it's also good to you.
也没什么不好 是吧
Take your maternal grandpa's last name,
你姓你姥爷的姓
then you'll also inherit
你姥姥的钱哪 房子啊
part of your grandma's house and money.
都有你的份
I promise,
我承诺啊
you'll also get your share
我们李家的医馆啊
of the clinic
房子啊
and the house of the Li family.
也都有你的份
What if I don't change it?
那我要是不改呢
You intend to disinherit me of them,
你打算剥夺我的继承权
don't you?
是吗
I didn't mean that.
没那个意思
I'm discussing it with you.
姑不是跟你商量呢吗
I just don't get it, Aunt.
我就不明白了 姑
You're a woman.
你也是女的
Why'd you prefer a boy over a girl?
你为什么要重男轻女呢
It's not the preference.
不是重男轻女
Aren't we in a special situation?
咱家不情况特殊吗
Let me tell you...
姑跟你
Yunjie!
云阶
Where are you going?
你去哪儿
None of your business!
管不着
The last person I want to see now
我现在最不想见到的人
is you!
就是你了
Are you able to walk?
行不行的
I've to do it.
不行也得行啊
The doctor said I need to walk.
大夫说还是要走一走的
Did the doctor say that?
大夫真这么说的
If you can't, go back and lie in bed.
不行就回去躺着
This is
这
Yunjie.
是云阶啊
Why is she squatting on the ground?
那怎么蹲这儿了
You go to see her.
去去 看看
Okay, you take care.
好好 你慢点
Yunjie,
云阶
why are you here?
你怎么蹲这儿啊
What's wrong?
你怎么了
Yunjie?
云阶
What's the matter with you?
怎么了 云阶
Don't cry!
不哭 不哭
What's going on?
怎么回事
Who bullied you?
谁欺负你了
Tell me!
你说话呀
Tell me.
你说
My aunt
大姑
told me to change my last name.
她让我改姓
What?
什么
I don't want to change it.
我不想改
Don't call her aunt anymore!
这大姑不要了
No need to change it, you know?
不需要改 我告诉你
Li Yungjie.
李云阶
Your name is always Li Yunjie!
这一辈子你都叫李云阶
No one in the world
在这世界上没有任何人
can change your name!
可以改变你
That's too much of her!
过分了真是
Lower your voice. We're in the hallway.
你小点声 在走廊呢
Yungjie, your dad's right.
云阶 你爸说的是对的
Your name won't be changed.
咱不改
Your name is Li Yunjie.
咱就叫李云阶
No one can change it.
没有人可以改
Your dad can decide it.
这事你爸就能做主
Yes!
对
You know?
知道吗
Just remember one thing.
你 你就记住一点
Mom gave birth to you
妈这辈子就生了你
and your brother.
跟你弟弟两个人
No matter
你不管你弟弟
what your brother's surname is,
以后姓什么
he's your biological brother.
他都是你亲弟弟
When mom and dad are old,
以后等爸妈都老了
you are
你们就是这个世界上
the closest siblings
最亲的人
in the world.
唯一的亲人
Get it?
知道吗
You've to guide him
你得管着他
and support each other.
然后互相帮衬着
Yunjie must be
我闺女肯定是
feel aggrieved.
受委屈了呀
Come and let Mom hug you.
快来给妈抱抱
Come.
来来来
Mom.
妈
My dear daughter, you're wronged.
妈心疼了 心疼了
My dear daughter.
心疼了
Mom and dad
妈和爸
have been waiting here for you.
一直在这儿等着你呢
We have something to discuss with you.
还要跟你商量事呢
What's it about?
什么事啊
Oh, brother.
弟弟啊
There is one thing
有个事情
I've to tell you.
要跟你商量一下
Here's the thing.
情况是这样的
Our aunt
大姑呢
hopes you to take Dad's last name Li.
想让你跟爸爸姓 姓李
Our grandparents
外公外婆呢
want you to take Mom's last name Xu.
想让你跟妈妈姓 姓许
Which one will you select?
你想选哪个呀
How could he answer you?
你觉得他能回答你
He couldn't.
不能
Let's not
我觉得
be in a dilemma.
咱们也别在这儿犯难了
Or else,
要不然
just get him your last name.
就让他跟你姓得了
My last name?
跟我姓
How can you face your family?
你能回得去啊
Can you explain about taking my last name?
那跟我姓你能回得去啊
Oh,
那合着
neither of us can't face our families.
我们俩都回不去了
I have an idea!
我有个主意
He'll neither name after you nor you.
不跟你姓 也不跟你姓
He'll name after me.
跟我姓
What's wrong?
怎么啦
You said
你们俩不是说
Little Grape is my biological brother
小葡萄是我亲弟弟
all my life.
是我一辈子的亲人吗
And I'm gonna lead him
而且我以后还要管着他
and take care of him.
照顾他呢
So, he can take my last name.
所以跟我姓
Any question about this?
有问题吗
No.
没问题啊
Good!
行
It's a deal.
那就这么愉快地决定了
My dear brother,
我亲爱的弟弟呀
you'll have a name.
以后你就有名字了
It's Li Yanwu.
叫李言午
Li Yanwu?
李言午
The Chinese word Xu combines Yan and Wu.
许字拆开就是言和午呀
My daughter has a lot of wisdom.
我闺女是有大智慧啊
That's a great name.
这名字起得好啊
It sounds like a leader's name.
一听就像前排就座的
He's gonna be a big shot.
以后就是大人物
That's good news for celebration.
这是个值得庆祝的事啊
Also,
还有
Yunjie's had an excellent performance
我们云阶
in her high school entrance examination.
中考成绩也非常优秀
It's also worth celebrating.
也值得庆祝的
Let's do it!
庆祝
We can eat fried chicken
吃炸鸡
and barbecue.
吃烧烤
Wonderful!
好
Mom,
妈
can you eat the food now?
你现在能吃吗
I...
我 我
I guess I can taste a little bit.
我应该可以吃一口的
But you guys can eat it.
但主要是你们吃
When you're enjoying it,
你们吃高兴了
I'll be happy.
我就高兴了呀
Perfect.
好
Place an order online.
下单吧
Order take-out?
叫外卖呀
If we go back to cook, they'll find out.
回去做他们就知道了
She is smart!
聪明
And thoughtful!
周全
Li Yanwu.
李言午
It's done.
好了
I've finished my homework.
姐姐作业写完了
It's time
现在就踏踏实实
to play with you.
陪你写作业
Little Grape.
小葡萄
Do dome exercise.
运动运动
Very good!
好棒
Wanna get up?
想起来吗
I've to be gentle.
慢点
You're great!
好棒啊
Had a full sleep?
睡饱了
You're so lovable.
这么乖呀
It's almost time.
五十九了
Come on.
来吧
She hung up.
她给我挂了
Why?
是什么意思啊
It's 7 pm.
七点了
The time is right.
没错呀
Yunjie?
云阶
[Hello, Dad.]
喂 老爸
What's your mom doing?
你 你妈在干什么呢
She was not answering my calls.
她不接我电话呢
My mom?
我妈
She is working.
工作呢吧
Work?
工作
What job is it?
什么工作啊
She didn't tell me.
她 怎么没跟我说啊
There's a lot you don't know.
你不知道的事多着呢
My mom seems to
我妈好像
have a project.
接了个什么项目
She is working on it at home.
在家忙着呢
Look, I'm babysitting my brother.
这不 帮她带娃呢
[Babysitting?]
你在带娃
[You? You're bragging!]
你会吗 你吹什么牛啊
Don't think I can't do it.
你瞧不起谁呢
You know what?
你信不信
When you come back,
这次你回来
he may not listen to you.
小葡萄不一定听你的
But he must listen to what I'm saying.
但他一定听我的
[He stops crying when I tell him to.]
我让他不哭他就不哭
He'll laugh when I ask him to.
我让他笑他就得笑
Don't brag.
你别吹牛
Let me see Little Grape.
你 你给我看看小葡萄
Show me
你给我看看
how you
你怎么逗他的
tickle him.
他怎么见了你就笑
Watch it.
看好了
Baby.
宝宝 宝宝
Little Grape.
小葡萄
[Call me Dad.]
爸爸
Call me Dad.
叫爸爸
Dad, Dad.
爸爸 爸爸
[Dear son.]
儿子
Why don't you smile?
怎么不笑呀
Give me a smile.
笑一个
[Yunjie!]
云阶
[Pick up the phone.]
你把电话拿起来
[Yunjie.]
云阶
Well.
这这
It's only more than a minute.
这才一分多钟啊这
I wanna see him more.
还不够啊
Good, He.
可以啊 小荷
This scheme
这个方案
got the right direction.
就朝这个方向走就行
You've grown a lot in 6 months!
你这半年长进不少啊
You've got a clear mind.
思路清晰了
Yeah, He.
对啊 小荷
Have your ideas straightened out?
你是不是突然开窍了
I was inspired by Meng'an.
是梦安姐启发了我
You can
你现在
take charge of the work alone.
可以独当一面了啊
Let's wrap it up.
今天就先到这儿吧
Okay?
好吧
We can discuss it next time.
回头再联系
What's up?
怎么了
Time to make the video call.
到点了 视频啊
It slipped my mind.
我忘了
I was in a meeting just now.
刚才开会呢
Didn't you make a video call to Yunjie?
你没打给云阶吗
She talked with me.
她跟我视频了
But it was just for a minute.
就视频一会儿
She hung up.
她就挂了
What...
你 你这 你这
what work are you doing?
忙 忙什么工作呢
Nothing.
也没什么
It's
就是
as same as before.
那个 跟你以前一样
I was doing a part-time job.
打打零工什么的
No need to do that.
你打什么零工啊
Listen up.
我跟你说
You'd better
你现在就得好好休息
have a good rest now.
多休息
You can't
你一宿一宿
sleep well all night,
也睡不着觉的
right?
是不是
All right.
行了 行了 行了
No more nagging.
你别絮叨了
Did you see Little Grape?
你刚才看小葡萄了吗
I only saw him for a minute.
我就看了一眼呢
Show him to me again.
你再给我看看
Okay. You'll see him again.
行行行 再让你看一眼
Let me show you.
再给你看一眼啊
I'm gonna show you.
给你看一眼啊
Your dad wanna see Little Grape.
你爸要看看小葡萄
Mom,
妈
why was he crying?
小葡萄怎么吭吭唧唧的
Is he hungry?
是不是饿了呀
No, it's not the time.
不能吧 没到点呢
Did he poo?
是不是拉了
You're right.
真的
Stinky!
太臭了
Hurry up! Take him away.
快快快 拿走拿走
I don't want the baby.
这小孩我不要了
What did you say?
什么不要了
Nonsense!
说什么呢
Hasten to get some water.
赶快去弄水去
Take a basin
拿个盆
and get some water.
弄点水
Are you cleaning it on my bed?
你在我床上弄啊
If not,
不在你床上弄
where can I do it?
在哪儿弄啊
Don't stain my sheet.
不许弄我床单上
Dear,
老婆
the
你这个
camera
你这摄像头啊
isn't filming the baby.
你不能 朝天呢这
I can't see him.
啥都看不了
It'll be done soon.
马上就好
Seriously? It's lunch time.
真是 马上就要吃饭了
But he pooed.
小葡萄拉粑粑
He is so small,
这么点的小孩
but his poo stinks.
拉屎臭死了
You're avoiding it?
你还嫌弃啥呀
You also shit when you were a baby.
你小时候不这样啊
Come on.
来啊
Quickly.
快
Tissues.
纸巾
With your reaction,
就你这样
aren't you embarrassed to brag
还好意思跟人家吹牛
that you help dispose
说这孩子是你
his shit and piss a lot?
一把屎一把尿拉扯大的
I don't care what you say!
随便怎么说都行
I just can't wipe his poop!
擦粑粑真不行
Well,
行了
go pour it.
倒了去吧
Don't wanna do it?
啊什么
I must say
以后吹牛
I pour his shit and the piss a lot.
改端屎端尿
All right, take your time.
好吧 你们忙吧
I...
我
I'll make the video call
我回头再跟你们联络啊
to you next time.
再跟你们视频
Well, I'm gonna hang up.
那我 那我挂了啊
It'll be done right away.
马上搞好 我的宝
I'm hanging up.
我挂了啊
Okay.
来
It's done.
好嘞
Let Mommy hold you.
妈妈抱啊
Baby.
我的儿
It's alright.
好嘞
Hello, everyone.
大家好
Please take a look.
大家可以看一下
For this baked finishing powder,
我的这一款烤制定妆粉
the half of the face with it
上脸的这一半呢
looks delicate and well.
非常地细腻和服帖
The other half of the face without it
那没有上脸的这一半呢
looks not that good.
就差一点意思
One of the fans
你看这有一位
asked that
我的家人说
if she could use this cosmetic
这款化妆品
during her pregnancy.
怀孕了可以用吗
So, our brand anchor
来 我们品牌主播
is gonna introduce it for you.
给大家介绍一下
This product
那我们这一款产品呢
is purely made from plants and natural.
是纯植物 纯天然的
It's mercury-free,
不含汞
lead-free,
铅
and without other harmful substances.
这一些有害的物质
I'm a mom
因为我本人
of two children.
是两个孩子的妈妈
So, I can
所以我可以
prove to you.
很负责任地告诉大家
Even if
它
you're in lactation
哺乳期
or gestation period,
怀孕期
you can use it with confidence.
都可以放心使用
I was shocked.
刚才真的震惊了
You are already
你已经是
a mother of two children.
两个孩子的妈妈了
Yeah.
对啊
You're great.
真的很伟大
How to address you?
品牌主播 你怎么称呼
Hi,
东子直播间的大家
everyone
姐妹们
in Dongzi Live Streaming Chat Room.
你们好
I'm Hot Mum.
我是辣妈许阿姨
Dongzi, thank you so much.
东子哥 这次谢谢你了
Not at all.
不客气
Thank you.
谢谢
Please see him off.
你送一下东子哥吧
Okay.
好
Thank you very much for your support.
这回谢谢你们啊
That's what we should do.
我们也是应该的
We need to cooperate a lot.
咱们以后常合作啊
Yeah, sure.
一定要合作啊
Contact us if there is business.
有机会要想着我们
Is Hot Mum
辣妈许阿姨
your personal account?
是你的个人号
Yes.
对
I've kept you in mind,
我记住你了
Hot Mum.
辣妈许阿姨
I think
我觉得
you have a good eye for products.
你选品很有眼光
You're very professional
在美妆赛道呢
in beauty makeup field.
也很专业
I believe we'll work together again.
有机会我们再合作
That will be great.
那太好了
In fact,
其实东子哥
I've learned a lot
我今天当你的助播
by working with you.
我学到了很多东西
So,
真的
thanks a lot.
谢谢你
My pleasure.
别客气
I'll link up with you privately on live.
我私下会跟你连线的
Bye-bye.
拜拜
Yes!
太好了
Don't call me with nothing serious.
没事打什么电话呀
I'm not available.
忙着呢
Why did she hang up as well?
怎么也给我掐了
What is she doing?
这都忙什么呢
Cook meals.
做饭
Finish cooking.
做完饭
Have the meal.
吃
Feed the baby.
给孩子吃
And Yujie needs to eat as well.
云阶得吃
Adults have to take turns eating.
大人得轮换着吃
Do the dishes.
洗碗
It's a tight schedule.
还是挺忙的
Meng'an's to check Yungjie's homework.
晚上还得给云阶看作业
Then it'll be 9 pm.
弄完了就得九点了
So, I've to put off
还得再把这视频的时间
the video call.
再往后挪一挪
I can call at 7 pm
要不就七点一次
and 9 pm.
九点再打一次
Dear!
老公
Look!
你快看
My follower has increased to 100,000.
我粉丝暴涨十万
Have you seen it?
你看到没
I've been making deliveries,
我这一直忙着发货呢
so, I've not noticed it, baby.
没注意啊 宝贝
You know what?
我跟你讲
The number could go up even more.
还能再涨呢
Do you believe it?
你信不信
What did you do?
你干什么了
Dongzi, the celeb anchor, followed me.
明星主播东子关注我了
Dongzi?
东子
He also asked me to join him on live.
他还让我跟他连线呢
Let me see what to wear.
我看看穿什么啊
How about this?
穿这个怎么样
I'm with a domineering lady style.
御姐范
He's younger than me.
他是弟弟
The fans will love to see our interaction.
大家喜欢看姐弟互动
Take a look.
你瞧一眼
Look.
看这个
How does it look?
怎么样
You think I'm old?
你是不是觉着我老了
Why do you interact with a younger man?
要找个弟弟啊
You're jealous.
你这醋吃得
You have dirty thinking.
怎么一股腐朽的味道
Quit it!
胡想什么呢
It's to draw more followers for account.
为了咱们家的账号涨粉
Really?
为了咱家账号
Get me a dress
给我拿一裙子
for me to interact with him online,
我跟他连线
I could get 100 thousand followers, too.
我也能涨十万粉
Here it is.
给
Put it on.
就这个
You think I dare not wear it?
你真以为我不敢穿啊
Just put it on.
穿
Little Grape's food
小葡萄的辅食啊
is simple.
很简单
It's rice paste.
就是米糊
Never put in more. Two spoonfuls are okay.
千万别多 两勺就够了
Want children to stay healthy?
要想小儿安
Don't overfeed him or overclothe him.
三分饥和寒
Come on, better for his mom to feed him.
来吧 妈妈喂
Okay.
好
You're good at it.
你是专家
Whatever you say!
都听你的
Let me feed him.
还是我来吧
Your hands just cleaned up the poop.
你那手 刚弄完粑粑
I washed my hands.
我洗手了
So?
那怎么的
You mean
按你这话说
my hands are useless after poop cleaning?
弄完粑粑 手剁了
Mom,
妈
I'll be honest.
我要批评你了
You always
你每次都不第一时间
don't put a harness on Little Grape.
给小葡萄戴上安全带
He becomes strong now.
小葡萄现在力气大了
It's dangerous for him not to wear it.
不绑安全带很危险的
What's the foremost in baby care?
带娃最重要的是什么
Safety.
安全
Come on, let me put on a harness?
来 我们绑个安全带
[Put on a harness.]
绑安全带
Baby specialist,
我说这位育婴专家呀
so, you just feed him
那你这是
but won't care about him pooing?
只管吃不管拉吗
Well, you haven't done a complete job.
那你这技术也不全面哪
No more talking about pooing.
别老拉拉拉的
Not decent.
不文明
A baby
小孩嘛
will
那不就是
shit and piss every day,
拉屎拉尿吗
right?
对吧
Right.
对
Mom!
妈
Okay. When Little Grape
好了 一会儿
finishes his food,
小葡萄吃完饭呢
we can have the meal.
咱们就开饭
Today's dish
今天呢
is Western food.
我做的是西餐
It's the one you taught me,
就是你教我的那个
the losing fat diet.
减脂减肥餐
Really?
真的吗
Are we gonna have vegetable?
那是不是要吃草呀
I've to eat that with my mom, too?
我也得跟着我妈吃草
Don't worry.
放心吧
I know you love meat.
我知道你爱吃肉
You'll eat steaks.
你吃牛排
Wonderful.
好嘞
We've even got steaks to eat?
还有牛排
[Little Grape, you're great.]
小葡萄真棒
Thanks to you,
这不是得托你们的福吗
I can cook western food now!
我现在都学会做西餐了
When I get back,
我回去以后啊
I'll show them off.
给他们炫耀一下
Yeah. Show them off!
炫耀
Don't eat out frequently.
以后少出去吃
Go for it!
加油
Alright.
好了
Get ready for dinner.
准备开饭
Okay.
好
Just eat it.
吃吧
Take more.
再吃一口
Open your mouth.
张嘴
Eat it.
吃一口 吃一口
Feed some to his mommy?
要不然 给他妈喂一口
Lower your voice.
轻点 轻点
Dear,
老公 老公
you know what?
我跟你说
The money
今天
I made today
今天一天赚的钱
is more than the income
比之前一个月赚的
of a whole month before.
都要多
Take a look.
你快看看
Look.
你看
Got 150 thousand followers today.
今天涨了十五万粉丝
Isn't that amazing?
厉不厉害
Yeah, dear.
太厉害了 老婆
I'm gonna do a good job tomorrow.
明天我要好好播
I've to keep
把东子引流给我的
all these woman fans
这些姐姐粉们
from Dongzi's attracted traffic.
全都留住
Woman fans are not that easy to get.
姐姐粉们很难吸的
But,
但是呢
their brand loyalty is high
她们品牌粘合度高
and they spend a lot.
消费能力也强
Look. We can also
你看 明天啊
make short videos like this tomorrow.
我们也拍这种短视频
Okay?
好不好
Today when I was working
我今天
with him,
给他当助播的时候
he was very pleased with me.
他对我特别满意
I was smart
你老婆当时可机灵
and added him as a WeChat friend.
立马冲过去加他微信
I gave him my account,
把我的账号推给他
then he accepted it right away.
他立马就加了
Isn't it cool?
给面吧
You're a mom of two children.
都两个孩子的妈了
Yet you were proactive to a man.
还弄得挺主动
You are a dad of two children.
那您这两个孩子他爹了
You were contacting female influencers
当初对那些女网红
back in the day, right?
不是也挺主动的吗
I'm a man!
我是男的
Hey, as a man, is it okay
男的就可以主动啊
to add friends on WeChat
就能加人微信啊
and then have a coffee
就能约人女网红
with a female influencer downstairs
在五星级酒店楼下
in a five-star hotel
喝咖啡
and let your wife see it by chance?
还被他老婆撞见了
You're still holding on to this thing.
还整一排比句
Are you settling a score with me now?
你这不是秋后算账吗
So what? Who started this?
那怎么的 谁先开始的
Okay, okay, you win.
好好好 你厉害
Look.
你跟我说啊
He brought you live streaming traffic,
给你引流
and added your WeChat.
俩人加微信
This is about
这他
business and money.
可都是真金白银 他
Why?
他
Why did he do that?
凭什么呀
Because I'm exceptional.
凭你老婆我优秀啊
I'm a top player
凭我在美妆主播界
in the beauty anchor business.
数一数二啊
He offered to sign a contract today.
他今天说要签我呢
He has a livestreaming team,
他有个直播家族
with lots of internet influencers.
底下有很多网红
If he signs a contact with me,
他要是签我
I'll be a big influencer as well.
你老婆我也红了
Don't do that.
不签
Why do you have to sign it with him?
为什么签他
We decided to start our own business
咱们说好了自主创业
and do living streaming on our own.
咱自己直播
Why do we need to sign it with him?
签他那儿干吗呀
Are you dumbhead?
你是不是傻
You are dumbhead.
你傻
When you're in his trap,
人到时候把你卖了
you'll be even helping him.
你给人数钱呢
You said I was dumbhead?
还我傻
You're. He is an internet celebrity.
你才傻 人家是大网红
He's willing to sign a contract with you
大网红愿意签你
and lead you.
带着你
What does that mean?
那是什么
It means you gotta seize the opportunity!
是机会 机会要抓住
Look how excited you are!
看把你激动那样
I think he's gonna seize you!
我看他是要抓你
Seize the opportunity...
还抓 抓
Who am I?
我是谁
Xu Mengxin.
许梦心
Who does Xu Mengxin belong to?
许梦心是谁的
Of course, it's...
那当然是
Take a look!
看看 看看
You make me startled!
你吓死我了
Extreme joy gives rise
乐极生
to sorrow!
悲
And you're even laughing at me.
你还嘲笑我
It hurts.
好痛啊
Sorry, sorry, dear.
对不起 对不起 老婆
That's pathetic.
太可怜了啊
You're on live streaming a lot
每天工作
that your mouth is dry.
口干舌燥的
You've worked hard.
辛苦啊
That's right.
就是
When you meet that guy in future,
以后你见他时候
you can do this.
你就这样啊
You do it like this.
你就这样
Then he'll sign the contract with you.
然后就这样让他签你哦
The pain is gone.
不疼了
I'm okay now.
好了
Am I awesome?
我厉害吧
Yes, you're.
你好厉害哦
Let's kiss again.
那再来一下
Hello, Dongzi!
你好 东子弟弟
Hello, Hot Mum!
你好 辣妈许阿姨
We meet again.
我们又见面了
Dear followers,
各位家人们
this is Hot Mum,
这位就是美妆主播
the beauty anchor.
辣妈许阿姨
Hello, everyone.
姐妹们 大家好
I'm Hot Mum.
我就是辣妈许阿姨
Welcome!
欢迎 欢迎
Welcome you.
欢迎辣妈许阿姨
You know,
许阿姨 你知道吗
my fans
我的粉丝家人们
miss you so much!
对你可是念念不忘啊
Since they knew we'd interact online,
听说我们要连线
the number of people online in our studio
我们直播间的在线人数
has increased by nearly 50 thousand.
已经激增五万人了
Well,
辣妈许阿姨
how about
要不要考虑一下
joining Dongzi' fan family?
加入到我们东子大家庭
Really?
真的吗
Can I?
可以吗
Dear fans,
各位家人们
do you welcome
大家欢不欢迎
Hot Mum
辣妈许阿姨
to join Dongzi's fan family?
加入到我们东子大家庭
If yes,
欢迎的
please input one
请在我们的公屏上
on the screen, please.
速速地扣一
If not, please input two.
不欢迎的请扣二
Now let's get the number rolling.
让我们的公屏滚动起来
There are a lot of ones.
好多扣一的呀
The ones are already all over the screen.
已经被扣一的刷屏了
Goodness,
辣妈许阿姨
you'd better
我觉得
think about it seriously.
你要认真地考虑一下了
Well, then I gotta give it some thought.
那我真得好好考虑一下
I'm looking forward to you
真的非常期待你加入到
joining us.
我们的大家庭
Alright.
好
Dongzi,
那东子弟弟
let's hurry up
我们话不多说
to introduce our first product.
开始推第一款产品吧
Hot Mom is so happy.
许阿姨真高兴
The fans number is soaring.
粉丝哗哗哗地涨
It's so great!
心情好极了
My assistant, please bring me
麻烦我的助播
the first product.
把第一款产品给我吧
Let Dongzi get it for you.
让你家东子弟弟给你拿
Ladies, hold on a second, please.
姐妹们 稍等一下哦
Because my helper
因为我的助播呢
is a little senior
年龄稍微有一点大
and elder than Dongzi.
他比东子弟弟要大一些
So, he reacts slowly.
腿脚不太利索
Let's wait a sec for him.
我们给他一点时间
He'll be here soon.
他马上就来了
He is coming.
来了 来了 来了
Here he is.
这就来了
What is it?
是一款什么呢
A Lipstick gift box.
口红礼盒
The box is amazing,
这款口红礼盒可厉害了
ladies.
姐妹们
Ten lipsticks
十支口红
with various colors are in it.
各式各样的颜色
It's for personal use or as a gift.
自用可以 送礼也可以
Mr Yu,
于总
as the founder of Blue Ocean,
你是蓝海的创始人
you can't bear
所以你舍不得
to do massive rectification of it.
大规模整改蓝海
In that case,
这样的话
it can't reach the expected target
是达不到
of our investors.
我们的投资预期的
No, Mr Zhao,
不 赵总
please
这样啊
let me explain.
您听 听我说啊
Please give me more time.
您再给我一点时间
I think Blue Ocean
我认为蓝海
is stable in our business foundation.
现在的基本盘是很稳的
It just takes time
盈利
for it to be profitable.
只是一个时间的问题
If we make a
如果现在
big rectification of Blue Ocean,
对蓝海进行整改
it's like acting with undue haste
这就操之过急了
and not the right way!
这是饮鸩止渴
You know?
你知道吗
Yu Hai,
于海
you should listen to us,
是你听我们的
and not object to us.
还是我们听你的
Now the majority shares of the company
现在蓝海股份的大头
are in our hands.
可在我们手上
You're just a small shareholder now.
你现在就是一个小股东
We can let you
我们可以让你
be the CEO.
做这个首席执行官
But if you
但是如果你
doesn't protect our interests,
不代表我们的利益
We can kick you out in a minute.
我们分分钟让你出局
All right, stop arguing.
好了 不要吵了
Let me say something.
我说两句啊
Mr Yu,
于总
your business capabilities
您的业务能力
are obvious to all.
是毋庸置疑的
The profit of Blue Ocean
蓝海从长期看
is positive in the long run.
盈利水平是乐观的
But you've to understand our position.
但你也得理解我们
What investors want is
投资人要的是
earn more money.
利益最大化
The capital investment has a deadline.
资本是有时间限制的
We have an exit mechanism.
我们有我们的退出机制
Hope you'll
我希望你能认真地
consider these suggestions
考虑下这些建议
thoroughly.
考虑清楚了
Then the
我们再进行
next conference call can be arranged.
下一次电话会议
Alright?
好吗
Meeting adjourned.
散会
Wanzhen,
婉真
I know you reminded me before.
我记得你之前提醒过我
Financing is a double-edged sword.
融资是一把双刃剑
Looks like I'm losing my bet.
看来我是要赌输了
I'm gonna lose
我要把整个蓝海
the whole Blue Ocean.
都输掉了
Sorry.
对不起
I didn't listen to you.
我没听你的
But do you really think
但是婉真 你也觉得
I should
我应该
give up control of the company?
放弃蓝海的控制权吗
Lin.
师哥
Yiduo.
一朵
Why haven't you gone back yet?
怎么还没回去呢
I have a telephone meeting
我一会儿
with a North America partner later.
有一个北美的电话会
It's so late.
这么晚了
Why are you still here?
你怎么也没走啊
I'm catching up with the progress.
提提速 赶赶进度
I hope
争取早一点
our lab
让我们的实验室啊
is able to go public and operate.
能够挂牌 运营
You're so hasten to do it.
这么着急啊
The earlier it's done,
实验室早点挂牌
the sooner
你们呢
experimental results you can get.
早点出实验成果
Then I can go home.
我呢 就可以早点回家
Honestly, if I don't go back soon,
说实话 我再不回去呀
my family will forget me.
我家里人快不认识我了
You're exaggerating!
你夸张的嘞
You're the breadwinner of your family.
你可是你们家的顶梁柱
I'm out there,
那顶梁柱在外边
so, it is my wife who
家里的房子谁顶啊
takes care of the family, right?
是吧
You've got something to say?
找我有事
I've got good news to tell you.
有个好消息要跟你分享
Have a seat.
坐
Okay.
好
A national-level
现在呢
biological lab
有一个国家级的
is
生物实验室
under preparation.
正在筹备
You're
他们很需要
very fit
你这样的人才
for the position of technical director.
去给他们当技术总监
I think
我觉得呢
after our lab
等咱们这个实验室
goes public,
顺利挂牌之后
I can recommend you to them.
我就可以推荐你去
Then you'll be in charge
这样 你就有两个
of lab projects.
实验室的项目在手
You can become
那你未来
a big shot
就是咱们这个行业的
in the field.
大拿了
What do you think?
怎么样